<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A copy of Mr. John Duries letter presented in Sweden to the truly noble and religious Lord Forbes: briefely intimating, the necessity of a common, fundamentall confession of faith amongst those Christians that receive the holy scriptures as the only rule of faith and practise, and in the scriptures, have the same apprehension of the tenour of Gods evangelicall covenant in Christ. The possibility of framing such a confession of faith, which infallibly shall be approved (by Gods grace) by all those that agree in these two fore-named principles. The manner of introducing this confession amongst them. Published by Samuell Hartlib. For the better improvement of Great Brittain's solemne covenant, and the advancement of truth, holinesse and peace amongst all Protestant churches. Licensed and entred according to order.</title>
            <author>Dury, John, 1596-1680.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 35 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A81912</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99871114</idno>
  <idno type="VID">123513</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240942084</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing D2849</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E251_8</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R212504</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99871114</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99871114e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A81912)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 123513)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 43:E251[8])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A copy of Mr. John Duries letter presented in Sweden to the truly noble and religious Lord Forbes: briefely intimating, the necessity of a common, fundamentall confession of faith amongst those Christians that receive the holy scriptures as the only rule of faith and practise, and in the scriptures, have the same apprehension of the tenour of Gods evangelicall covenant in Christ. The possibility of framing such a confession of faith, which infallibly shall be approved (by Gods grace) by all those that agree in these two fore-named principles. The manner of introducing this confession amongst them. Published by Samuell Hartlib. For the better improvement of Great Brittain's solemne covenant, and the advancement of truth, holinesse and peace amongst all Protestant churches. Licensed and entred according to order.</title>
                  <author>Dury, John, 1596-1680.</author>
                  <author>Hartlib, Samuel, d. 1662.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by G.M. for Thomas Vnderhill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1643.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dated at end: Stockholme this 24. of Jann. 1637.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Nou: 15".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Theology, Doctrinal --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  Church history --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-01 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-01 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:123513:1"/>
            <p>A COPY OF M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. <hi>JOHN DƲRIES</hi> LETTER Presented in <hi>Sweden</hi> to the truly Noble and Religious Lord FORBES: <hi>Briefely Intimating,</hi> The Necessity of a Common, Fundamentall Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession of Faith amongst those Christians that receive the holy Scriptures as the only Rule of Faith and Practise, and in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, have the same apprehension of the Tenour of GODS Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelicall Covenant in CHRIST.</p>
            <p>The Possibility of framing such a Confession of Faith, which infallibly shall be approved (by Gods grace) by all those that agree in these two fore-named Principles.</p>
            <p>The Manner of introducing this Confession amongst them.</p>
            <p>Published by <hi>Samuell Hartlib,</hi> For the better improvement of <hi>Great Brittain's</hi> solemne Covenant, and the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement of Truth, Holinesse and Peace amongst all Protestant Churches.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="license">
                        <p>Licensed and Entred according to Order.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>G. M.</hi> for <hi>Thomas Ʋnderhill,</hi> 1643.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:123513:2"/>
            <head>A Copy of M. <hi>Iohn Duries</hi> Letter, presented in <hi>Sweden</hi> to the truely Noble and Religious Lord <hi>Forbes, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Eeing you have been pleased not onely to take notice of these meane endeavours of <hi>Ecclesiasticall Pacification</hi> which I have prosecuted, but also to offer your favourable assistance in furthering the same to a hopefull issue: I acknowledge my selfe bound to give thankes unto God on your behalfe, and to satisfie all your desires concerning my purpose in following out (as it shall please God to enable mee) these intensions, that both your selfe and such others as you shall oblige to Cooperate to wards the furtherance of this Cause, may by this briefe Information know how and what to vndertake, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joying profitably, through the communion of Saints, the fruits of their spirituall gifts towards the raising up of this <hi>Tabernacle</hi> of holy Concord amongst Protestants. The things which are already knowne to you, either by the <hi>Latine Narrative</hi> or by other Writings and circumstances of our conversations together, I will not touch; onely that which is most materiall to be considered by all that from their hearts seek the advancement of the Gospell of <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Peace</hi> in these our dayes, I shall (God willing) here mention, in shewing three points, to which the summe of all thoughts and endeavours in this nature may bee referred. The first is concerning the necessity of a common Fundamentall confession of Faith amongst those Christians that receive the holy scriptures as the only Rule of Faith and Practise, and in the scriptures have the same apprehension and conception of the tenour of God, his Evangelicall Covenant in Christ. The second is concerning the Possibility of framing such a Confession of Faith which infallibly shall be approved (by Gods grace) by all those that agree in these two fore-named Principles. The third is concerning the Manner of introducing this <hi>Confession</hi> amongst them, that it may be a Meanes of spirituall <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Ʋnity</hi> in composing all schismaticall differences and scandalls. To these three heads all meditations tending to ripen these counsels, and all enterprizes tending to work out the effect of the same, may be reduced. And it appeareth by all three that one position is laid as the ground-worke of all this negotiation, which is this that the onely Meanes to reunite devided Protestants, and knit their Churches together in a bond of brotherly love is, to bring them to make publick profession of one and the same Confession of Faith in respect of Fundamentalls. For I find it to be agreed upon, and yeilded on all sides, that if the Fundamentall Truthes of Faith and Practise be acknowledged and professed by two Churches, that those Churches ought for this cause to professe sisterly love one towards another, and that they ought not for some differences in things not fundamentall, to breake the <hi>vnitie of the Spirit</hi> through unprofitable debatements. For seeing we are expressely commanded to endeavour to keepe the <hi>unitie of the Spirit in the bond of peace. Ephes:</hi> 4. 3. therefore it plainely followeth, that it is not lawfull to be at <hi>strife</hi> and <hi>variance</hi> for matters which by the propertie of their nature inferre not a division of the spirit. Now it is certaine that no <hi>diversitie</hi> of <hi>opinions</hi> in things Extrafundamentall, by which the truth of <hi>Faith, Hope and Charity</hi> is not overthrowne in a mans heart, can by the property of its nature inferre such a <hi>division,</hi> and therefore for such a <hi>diversitie of opinions,</hi> peace and brotherly <hi>love</hi> ought not to be violated. Now if it could bee made plaine to the devided <hi>Protestant Churches,</hi> that indeed the causes of their divisions are Extrafundamentall, it may be truly and hopefully conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that for <hi>conscience sake</hi> towards God and for their mutuall <hi>Edification</hi> and <hi>Preservation</hi> against the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:123513:2"/> incroaching power of darkenesse, they would bee moved to leave of <hi>passionate disputations</hi> and laying aside the causes of their separation to compose their differences in brotherly love. But here now lyeth the greatest difficultie of this whole Worke, how to make this matter plaine vnto them; for all <hi>parties</hi> stand upon their owne <hi>Justification,</hi> and to make their cause good, they will readily censure and condemne others highly, and least they should seeme to contend so earnestly without a sufficient cause, they fall commonly to maintayne that the adverse partie runneth into <hi>Fundamentall Errors,</hi> from whence they pretend to shew that the cause of their <hi>division</hi> is a <hi>Fundmentall Necessitie.</hi> Thus while every one doth justifie his owne separation from others and that by upbrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of errors Contrafundamentall, from hence ariseth the difficultie, whereof I spoke even now, that it is very hard to make it plaine to the <hi>divided Churches,</hi> that the true causes of their divisions are Extrafundamentall. For if you will goe directly to worke and maintaine this position, you enter into a <hi>labyrinth</hi> of <hi>contradictions,</hi> and shall have to doe with every ringleader of a partie, and withall shall be driven to debate more about Errors and Offences then about Truths and holy Duties, which is a worke in this <hi>negotiation</hi> mainely unprofitable, and if you doe not maintaine the position, but labour to make men <hi>peaceable by Paraeneticall Discourses,</hi> you loose your <hi>labour.</hi> For a good <hi>conscience</hi> will not permit a man to professe himselfe a Brother to him, whom he thinketh to remaine stubbornely in a Fundamentall Error: neither can the affections of <hi>vnion</hi> spring up in the heart of him whose understanding is fully infected with the roote of separation. Now the roote of separation is nothing else but this opinion, which one partie taketh up against another, that it lyeth in <hi>Fundamentall Errors,</hi> and to roote out this <hi>weed</hi> from mens understandings, wee must not proceed <hi>per Regulam falsi,</hi> in searching out the Errors of all sides to demonstrate them not to bee Fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall, but because <hi>veritas est norma sui &amp; obliqui:</hi> we must draw mens thoughts and consciences to reflect with a single eye upon Truths Fundamentall, that after wee have comprehended all things <hi>necessary for salvation</hi> in our mindes, then wee may be brought to see that wee ought to be have our selves as Brethren towards all such as have the same feeling with us in these things. So then, wee see by this how in the <hi>Worke of Pacification,</hi> and wherefore it is necessary to search out <hi>Fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall Truthes,</hi> and to have the same to bee brought into a <hi>For me of a Confession,</hi> that in the <hi>Ʋnitie of the spirit</hi> being sealed up, the Consciences of all Men that tremble at the Word of God, may find them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves obliged to keepe it stedfastly, in the <hi>bond of Peace.</hi> This Necessity of a <hi>Fundamentall Confession</hi> is in this case of <hi>Pacification</hi> so absolutely great, that I feare not to affirme that without such a <hi>Confession</hi> it is impossible to re-unite the devided spirits, and through it there is no doubt, but all the godly may be easily re-united and the ungodly children of <hi>strife</hi> so far repressed, that they shall not be able to cloake any longer their selfe-willed frowardnesse, with the imputation of <hi>Fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall Errors</hi> against their <hi>supposed Adversaries.</hi> But besides this argument of the Necessitie of a <hi>Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall Confession of faith</hi> amongst <hi>Protestants,</hi> there bee many others of great waight and impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, whereof we purpose to touch briefely the summary heads, that all such as seeke the building up of the <hi>misticall body</hi> of Iesus Christ, and that wish for the <hi>gathering</hi> together of the <hi>Saints in the vnitie of faith and knowledge of the Sonne of God,</hi> by the faithfull discharge of the worke of the Ministery may be stirred up in the <hi>feare</hi> of God to contribute their talents to further this effect: Here then the necessitie of bringing <hi>a Fundamentall Confession</hi> to passe may bee seene, either in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect of <hi>Christianity</hi> it selfe, or in respect of the <hi>Protestant Churches</hi> ioyntly, or in respect of every particular <hi>Church</hi> severally, or in respect of the <hi>Ministeriall duties</hi> to be discharged in every Church, or lastly in respect of every particular person who hath a care of his eternall salvation. Now if it be found necessary for the good of all these, who is the man that would not helpe to bring it to light? I say first that it is Necessary for the state of <hi>Christianity,</hi> that <hi>Jewes, Turkes, and Heathens</hi> (for who knoweth how neare the day of their <hi>visitation</hi> may bee) may have a true summe of Christianity, to know what it is: for so long, as such a Common <hi>Confession</hi> is wanting, it cannot be possibly knowne to them, but readily they esteeme all Christianity by the apprehension which they have of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:123513:3"/> such which are noe Christians in deed, but in name. Therefore not to suffer this aspersion, to lye upon Christianity, such a Fundamentall Confession is necessary. And moreover it is necessary for such as have to deale with Jews, Turks and Heathens in respect of Religion. For if either they bee put to the defence of their owne faith and profession, or if they have occasion to enforme those that are not yet called to the name of Christ (if perhaps God might convert them) how shall they be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to performe understandingly, either the one or the other, so that they shall not contradict any that may come after them, to deale with the same persons, in the same nature, except they know what the common undeniable <hi>Fundamentals</hi> are, wherein all Christians agree? If they know this, then they goe safely to worke, but if they know it not, they can neither defend not teach Christia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity rightly: therefore in this respect it is necessary.</p>
            <p>As for the state of Protestant Churches ioyntly taken, whether you consider them in respect of their <hi>Enemies</hi> the <hi>Papists,</hi> or of their halfe friends the <hi>Grecians,</hi> or of themselves one towards ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: This is every way <hi>absolutely necessary,</hi> both for the full discovery and overthrow of the <hi>Man of sinne,</hi> and for the gaining of the remnant of <hi>Gods Election</hi> out of <hi>Babylon</hi> in a publike way, and for the confirming and perfecting of the <hi>foundation</hi> laid or left amongst the <hi>Grecians.</hi> And lastly, for the preservation and edification of one Protestant Church towards another, which for want of this are now come to study one anothers overthrow, to eate up and persecute one another. So that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly the <hi>Judgement</hi> will come to the height, except by this meanes the Lord will be pleased to prevent it. A man might write a Volume of the Necessity of a <hi>Fundamentall Confession</hi> in this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect, but because to all judicious men the case is out of doubt, therefore I will speake no more of it.</p>
            <p>As for the state of every particular Church by it selfe, the matter might not seeme very necessary, seeing every Church hath it's owne <hi>Confession</hi> for it selfe, wherein it supposeth to have all the <hi>Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentals</hi> sufficiently expounded, and therefore may thinke it needlesse, at least not necessary to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed further for matters <hi>Fundamentall.</hi> But this is a great cause of our <hi>inevitable misery,</hi> and of these <hi>infinite divisions</hi> and <hi>subdivisions</hi> in all Churches, that the <hi>Confessions</hi> which at first were put forth as testimonies against Papistry, are now either rashly contradicted, mis-interpreted and called in que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion by some, or else too highly urged and pressed upon Men by others. As if the whole tenour of all their Articles were infallible <hi>Fundamentall Truthes,</hi> the disabuse of all <hi>Confessions,</hi> which trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleth more or lesse every Church, maketh one truely Fundamentall and infallible Confession to be necessary to them all, to avoid the ruine which threatneth every one of them. For to any judicious man that can discerne the state of Particular Churches, and how one particular Confession is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come <hi>a stone of offence,</hi> either by way of opposition, or else by way of comparison unto another, and how every Confession (though true and good) is neverthelesse too weake to keepe <hi>Ʋnity in the spirits</hi> of those children which it hath begotten, can without much discourse perceive that both to take away their oppositions and comparisons, and to strengthen their weaknesses, a common <hi>Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentall Confession,</hi> which will be the infallible truth of God, and a true roote of them all, must be proposed, that they may see that they are all like different branches springing through one tree, from the same root of life: So then to this effect also such a <hi>Confession</hi> is necessary. As for dischar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of <hi>Ministeriall duties,</hi> whether they be <hi>Preaching</hi> and <hi>Praying, Exhorting</hi> or <hi>Reproving, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forting</hi> or <hi>Threatning, Instructing</hi> or <hi>Correcting,</hi> nay <hi>Meditating</hi> or <hi>Writing,</hi> all this is done with so little fruit and effect (as alas) may be seene every where, all this is done in many places with of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence and destructions of the hearers <hi>Faith,</hi> chiefly for want of an <hi>insallible Rule</hi> and <hi>fundamentall un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted Principles,</hi> from whence and by which all particular duties in this nature might be squared, and all conclusions and positions might be inferred and made cleare to a Christian conscience. Now this <hi>Rule</hi> and these <hi>Principles</hi> may be had in a <hi>Fundamentall Confession,</hi> which for this respect is as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary, as for any other hitherto named. For from this defect in matters belonging to <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steriall Duties</hi> all other inconveniencies hitherto named originally flowe, therefore the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:123513:3"/> of this is the helpe of all the rest, and I see not how it can be done without a <hi>Fundamentall Confession.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Lastly, a <hi>Fundamentall Confession</hi> is necessary for every particular man, that would be sure of the <hi>knowledge necessary to salvation.</hi> To demonstrate this, what is it needfull, is it not as cleare as the Sunne at noone day, that by reason of the endlesse doubts and disputations, of the schoole tearmes foisted into divinity, and of the bitternesse and malice of parties in maintaining their owne and traducing their adverse parties tenets, that the simple plaine man, is in a thousand perplexities and labyrinths, if he be zealous to search for knowledge, and if he be not zealous, must remaine in unset<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led ignorance? And that the worldly wise man either denieth all Religion, and becometh an Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ist, or else setleth it in the tenour of some certaine opinions, and in the formality of some outward Worship: And that even the Schollers and Men of learning themselves are wrapped into <hi>inextri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable confusions</hi> in their differences, and know not how to right themselves, to their owne or other mens edification: And all this befalleth unto all these onely for want of a <hi>Fundamentall Confession,</hi> whereby to rule and principle themselves and others in their Actions and Meditations; This de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect in this respect cannot be sufficiently described nor lamented, and therefore I will leave it to the more inward and scrious thoughts of the godly wise, who seeketh not himselfe, but as Christ did, the good of many for their edification.</p>
            <p>This is the Necessity of a Fundamentall Confession. As touching the Possibility of framing the same, so that it shall be infallibly received by all those that acknowledge the holy Scriptures to be the only Rule of Faith and Obedience, and take the scope of the Scriptures (the Covenant of God in Christ) in the same sense, I will briefly set downe my conception.</p>
            <p>First, then I suppose that all such as have the same Principles of the Scripture, and of the Covenant may easily be brought together, or else to admit of the same conclusions, which are inseparably or fundamentally dependant from those principles, if their minds be not fore-stalled with a preconcei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved thought and passion, or if they follow the right Method of scripturall and spirituall Meditation to cleare their doubts when they doe arise.</p>
            <p>Secondly, I doe suppose, that two, three or more men spiritually affected and void of partiality may agree together to set upon this worke of framing a Fundamentall Confession.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, I suppose that they may know the right Method of doing it, and following the same without wavering. All these things are not impossible, but yet in all this, there is as yet no evidence of Possibility, how to performe the Worke, and to performe it so, that no man may find fault with it, who admitteth the truth acknowledged amongst Protestants concerning the Scriptures and the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of the Gospell. Now then to come to the Manner of proceeding in this Work, I think that all the Places of Scripture chiefly in the New Testament, which speak of the Covenant of God, should be gathered together by the way of a most plaine Analysis reduced to simple Axioms in such a form as I have given you an example in a place of <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. When this is done, let them observe all the different Matters w<seg rend="sup">ch</seg> are mentioned in all these Places, and let every Matter be noted distinctly by it self; for it is to become a chiefe head of some Fundamentall Truth afterward. The Matters thus distinctly no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted must be afterward conferred together, that their Subordination and Coherence one with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, may be conceived. If this be rightly performed, as easily it may be done, then if not the whole, at least the chiefe matter and the Order of the parts of the Fundamentall Confession is found out, and it is found out from the Scripture it selfe without any addition: So that no true Christian can be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to except any thing against it. This being effected, then every particular Matter and chiefe Head is to be enlarged just in the same fashion, as this fore-named Matter of the Covenant was enlarged, by collecting all Places that speake of it, by Analysing the same into single Axiomes, and by confirming the Axiomes together, to set them in their due Subordination. For here perhaps it will not be need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to note againe every particular Matter by it selfe to become a chief head of another enlargement, because after the first Amplification, the Truthes which may be superadded, will not all be Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:123513:4"/> and absolutely necessary to salvation, to be expresly known or firmly conceived, but if a man will amplifie matters the second, third and fourth time by this same Method, taking alwayes one thing out of the bosome of another, he may doe it for his owne and others edification, and will per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the degrees of Spirituall Truthes, how that one ariseth from another, which Truthes, although they will all be truly infallible, yet they must not all be esteemed Fundamentally Necessary for salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, so that without the knowledge of the same, a man doth faile in the substance of the New Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, but yet chiefly in the second and third amplification, they will all be Saving Truthes and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of large extent, for knowledge and practise. Now when the first amplification of the Matter is performed, if a man would be sure to have omitted no Doctrine or Matter necessary for salvation, let him seeke out and call to mind all the Places of Scripture, which have a Marke of Necessity or a speciall Promise of Salvation annexed expressely unto them. These places must be in like manner A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalyzed into simple Propositions, and if you thinke good their Matters may be enlarged as the former Matters were. These Matters, if they be different from these of the Covenant, may be set by themselvs in their severall Subordinations. If men that are in different places have the same Scripturall book of Concordance (for nothing else but the Originall Text, and a faithfull Dictionary to know the true property of every word is requisite to go about this worke) and follow punctually this <hi>Method,</hi> they cannot almost faile to make the same <hi>Fundamentall Confession</hi> word by word. Perhaps the Order of the Matters may differ, but all the Truthes will be <hi>verbatim,</hi> the very same positions. Now what eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man of judgement in following Scripture would doe, if he were to make a <hi>Fundamentall Confessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> for himselfe, he will never reject, when he shall find it done by another. This then is the <hi>Possibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> of framing such a <hi>Confession</hi> as will rectifie all our confusions, and of framing it, so that it will be altogether without exception, neither can any insufficiency be alleadged against it, for which in times to come, it can be found unfit to determine matters of doubt, whether in point of knowledge, or of practise, if it be rightly made use of and applied to the case (which commeth in question) with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out partiality. When the <hi>Confession</hi> is thus framed, it will be easie to demonstrate, that every Article of it is absoluely Necessary for salvation, either to be beleeved and known, or else practised. For it will containe all the Fundamentalls and little or nothing more then the Fundamentalls of both, And to build upon this foundation there is nothing more requisite then to Meditate and Analize diligently the scriptures; Thus then the Confession is framed. Now to speake of the Introducing of it into all Churches, I thinke it not very needfull, because we are not yet come so far in the Worke; yet because it may be profitable to give men well affected to the publike good, occasion to thinke upon this also, I will open my selfe herein as in the former matters. Thus then I do conceive, that because all the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitions of such a Confession will be absolutely undeniable, that therefore it cannot be rejected by any, but being proposed it will be received, chiefely if men be informed of the Manner how they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selvs may make the very same Confession from the Scriptures. If men make a scruple of the sufficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of it, to rectifie mens Iudgements in matters of doctrin or Action then, the use of it must be made plain, &amp; a Method shewed, how it should be applied to all Cases of doubts &amp; how with it the Method of simple Analysis of the Scriptures may and ought to concurre, when doubts are Extrafundamentall, which things being as plainely shewed as this former hath been, and being found as evidently in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible as this is, (because these latter manners of proceeding in the application of the Confessiō to resolve doubts, or in analyzing the scriptures to the same effect, differeth nothing from the way which is used in the very framing of the Fundamentall Confession) no man of any conscience will be able to refuse. This sheweth the Possibility, that the Confession being proposed may and will bee received. But much lyeth in the first hint or manner of proposing every thing, neither is this in any mans hand but in Gods will, who hath the times and seasons of all occurences and the fit occasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of all actions in his owne disposing, and according as men are acquainted with the course of Gods dealing or are capable to observe his Counsell, by reason of some intimacie with his inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, so they get hints or opportunities to doe some part of his worke in that whereunto he hath
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:123513:4"/> enabled them. As for mee I have been hitherto as it were knocking at the doore of a holy Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion and Correspodencie about this businesse, but by reason of the tumults of warrs, and outward distractions of mens mindes, that looke no further then the appearance of things, not being able to penetrate into Gods counsell, and way of propagating his Gospell, and by reason of my owne bodily and spirituall wants and insufficiencies, which are yet lying heavily upon mee, and by reason of spirituall Clamours and complaints, partly over injuries, vexations, oppressions and tyranicall persecutions of mens consciences, partly over selfe-willed conceitednesse, and scandalous practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses which rise upon all sides, my weake voice hath not hitherto been heard, because Gods time was not yet come to open mens hearts to consider the matters that belong to the Vniversall Good of all Churches, and because wee find by experience, that even the best and most Spirituall Men in these dayes, are either disheartened from publike endeavours, through their own fearefullnesse, or beaten of through Authority, or stopped in the undertaking, and agitating of matters belonging to Christianity (absolutely considered in it selfe, as it may be equally profitable to all divided parties) by reason of a secret partiality and love to their owne parties, for the maintaining, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagating of which, they bend all their thoughts, so that they can find no time to thinke upon any other matters of so large an extent as may reach to the good of all, but if the more understanding sort of our best men now adaies would consider, that God would have the members of Christs mysti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call body to grow as the members of a naturall body use to doe, that is altogether all a like in their proportion and all one by and through another, perhaps they would have more universall thoughts and mind things, especially in the Gospell more appliable to the good of all sides then now they doe, whilst in a Zeale for Religion and Truth they mind more the good of one then all. Now it is cleare unto mee that God will not have any Church to come unto perfection without the rest. For even as he would not have the ancients who retained a good report. <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. to come to perfection without us, so he will not have us to come to perfection one without another, or all without our Posteritie. This being truly apprehended by such as have Vniversall gifts, and a spirit to conceive of the publike good of many, may be a meanes to further the Correspondency, which all this while I have been suing for in spirituall matters, and to ripen the fruits of that seed which is already or may be sowne hereafter, in a holy Communion of Religious duties setled towards the prosecuting of true Peace or of Peace in truth according to these Principles. For indeed all that I have been doing hitherto in all parts, is nothing else but the sowing of these Principles and such like, as I have propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed to these of the Vniversity of Vpsall, what fruite, where, and when it will spring up, God onely doth know, neither have I any other care or policie, but to see and stand upon my watch, and to know what opportunities of holy Communion, God doth offer in this nature unto mee. For I know that the Communion of Saints (beleeved in the Creed verbally by many, but practised in effect by very few) amongst men that have a speciall care to deny themselves as well in spirituall as in temporall things of a present nature, is the only Instrument which God doth make use of to build up his Church, and by meanes contemptible to the world to worke great effects. So then in this you doe see all my way and policie, both for Theorie and Practise in this worke: which in a word is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing else but a Solicitation (private or publike as it falleth out) of a godly Communication of coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sells and endeavours amongst the learned of this age for spirituall Peace and Vnitie to be procured by a Fundamentall Agreement in matters belonging to Knowledge and Practise according to the Scriptures.</p>
            <p>Therefore if you, by the addresse of Gods providence, doe light upon any fit man, able and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to correspond with mee in this nature, I entreate you to give them information of that which you know concerning my proceedings; and If it be found expedient, I would wish to heare in due time from them to bee participant of the fruits of Grace which Gods Spirit will powre upon them, for the good of the Common wealth of Israell. I need not mention what an entry and progresse God hath given here unto mee, and what (if his blessing continue) the issue may bee, if it be lawfull
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:123513:5"/> for us in these matters to make rationall coniectures. You know all the particulars, whic<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> I can say in this behalfe, onely one thing I will mention, concerning my purpose o<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> introducing the forenamed Fundamentall Confession into all the Churches, and therewit<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> make an end, and that is this. If it please God to dispose so of the issue of my treatis<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> with the divines of Sweaden, that I may reach the effect intended, then my thought is t<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> propose the matter to the chiefest worthies of all the Churches, beginning at <hi>Scotland, Eng<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gland and Jreland,</hi> and so proceeding to the rest, as God shall open a doore, and after the chiefe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thies (if God permit) J conceive it might be brought to the Vniversities, and from the Vniversities to greater, either ordinary, or (as it may fall out either for this or other cause) extraordinary Meetings. This is but spoken at adventure to intimate the way of proposing and introducing the Fundamentall Confession by degrees, and this may be done with greater speed and facilitie then most men are a ware of. If it please God to bring once the matter to this period, that nothing is to be thought upon, but to make this Proposal. Yet I love not to settle any resolutions upon such probable coniectures, I love not to leade Gods Worke, but rather to bee led by him in it as hee thinkes good. He know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth where the first fruit of this sowing shall spring up, hee hath prepared of old all the Workemen fit for this Husbandry, and hee hath them in readinesse: what presumption were it then for us to seem to prescribe any thing to his counsell, and to predetermine to our selves either the issue, or the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular way of driving forward his Worke. I am fallen lately in love with this opinion, that it is very good for us in matters of dutie towards God and chiefely in this Worke, to see no possibility in respect of Men, and outward meanes to effect it. Many reasons might be alleadged to shew why this is very good, but one that pleaseth mee much is this, because that I suppose him to be noe true servant of God, and so indeed not fit to joyne in this Worke, that will not undergoe a matter of duty without the foresight of the issue. He that will not loose his labour for Gods sake, nay and bee ill rewarded for his paines, hee is unworthy to bee imployed in his service. And honest men that mind Gods Cause without any respect, but because it is his will and Cause are well ridd of such company, not, but that all in their own lawful way and degree in some things may be made use of, but all the secrets of mens resolutions, must not be concredited, except they bee knowne to have both the faith and obedience of our Lord Iesus Christ without partiallity, that is without minding themselves or their owne plots and minding onely Gods will, and All Gods will, and towards All Gods Children and that upon all occasions, without much demurring and preconjectures. To men of this disposition, that you shall meete withall, I pray you to have mee and this Worke recommen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that I may bee remembred by them before the throne of Grace, and that I may bee partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pant of the thoughts which the Spirit of grace shal put in their mind for the setting forward of these endeavours. With such I desire to entertaine Correspondency and to such I offer my self as a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Servant of the Communion of Saints in Iesus Christ, to whose favour and safeguard I commend both them and your selfe in all your wayes, as being</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honours most dutifull<lb/> and humble Servant in Christ<lb/>
                  <hi>Iohn Durye.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>Stockholme<lb/>
                  <date>this <hi>24.</hi> of Jann. <hi>1637.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>